<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iudgement of an old grand-jury-man of Oxford-shire, concerning the breaking up of the late treaty begun at Uxbridge 30. Ian. 1644. Delivered upon his perusall of the late printed full narration of the passages concerning it.</title>
            <author>Old grand-jury-man of Oxford-shire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E285_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E303_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200068</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158516)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E285[8] or 50:E303[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iudgement of an old grand-jury-man of Oxford-shire, concerning the breaking up of the late treaty begun at Uxbridge 30. Ian. 1644. Delivered upon his perusall of the late printed full narration of the passages concerning it.</title>
                  <author>Old grand-jury-man of Oxford-shire.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"On the King's side"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy at E.285[8]: "May 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IVDGEMENT OF AN OLD <hi>GRAND-J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY-MAN</hi> OF OXFORD-SHIRE, CONCERNING THE BREAKING UP OF THE LATE TREATY Begun at UXBRIDGE 30. <hi>Ian.</hi> 1644.</p>
            <p>Delivered upon His peruſall of the Late Printed FULL NARRATION of the Paſſages concerning it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> Printer to <hi>the Vniverſity,</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:158516:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158516:2"/>
            <head>THE JUDGEMENT OF AN OLD GRAND-JURY-MAN of <hi>Oxford-ſhire,</hi> Concerning the breaking up of the late TREATY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the ſadneſſe of our Dayes, and the ſhortneſſe of our Nights, may ſeem to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance all old merry Stories, as being <hi>unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable:</hi> yet before they be <hi>unlawfull</hi> too, (for They at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> may chance to Vote downe <hi>Tales,</hi> as they have done <hi>Stage-playes</hi>) I ſhall venture to tell <hi>One</hi> unto the World: conceiving I may fairly deſire pardon for the unſeaſonableneſſe thereof, when it ſhall appeare, that none have deſerved more puniſhment, then They which have made it, moſt of all, in Seaſon. It is an old Story of the <hi>Horſe</hi> &amp; the <hi>Hind,</hi> which I have heard my Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father tell many a Winter night, when I was a boy; But I dare ſay, I ſhould never have remembred it, if the reading of the <hi>Full Relation of the Paſſages concerning the late Treaty at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> which was lately Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſent me down into the Country by a Friend, had not renewed the decayed Impreſſions and Images thereof, and brought them all freſh againe into my mind. And the Tale, which he told, was this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Horſe and the Hinde,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>were feeding in a goodly piece of Encloſed ground, where there was graſſe enough; and at laſt downe comes the Horſe to a Brook running thereby, with a deſire to drinke; The Hinde tripping here and there over the plaine, at laſt chanc't to take the water, in that very quarter or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158516:3"/>diviſion, where the Horſe was drinking: and in the paſſage, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing the clearneſſe of the water, hindred the Horſes draught, and made him life up his head. Which the Horſe took ſo ill, that forthwith he addreſſes himſelfe unto the Keeper of the Parke, and in a moſt importunate manner, ſues to him for Juſtice, againſt the poore Hinde. This Keeper having ſo much of the fence of a Juſtice in him as to ſmell any ſommodity that was comming near him, promiſes to doe him right: and he would teach the Hinde to spoyle more graſſe then he could eat, and to trouble the water which the Horſe ſhould drinke, I marry, that he would onely this one thing, he deſtred of the Horſe, by way of Accommodation to his Revinge, and that was: that the Horſe would let him bridle him, and back him ſtraight, whileſt the Hinde was now in ſight, and he doubted not but inſtantly to overtake him, and lay him dead before him. The Horſe accepts of the Condition in all haſt: and after two or three heats, the poore Hinde falls, At which the Horſe does ſeeme not a little to rejoyce, in confidence, that all the whole Parke, and the River too, will now be his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any moleſtation or diſturbance. But in the concluſion, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nothing ſo: for the Keeper finding it more for his eaſe to ride, then he did to goe on foot, and having now the bridle in his owne hands, would never be perſwaded to let it ſlip againe, for all the Horſes entreaties: but hurried him from this place to that, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him over this ditch and that hedge, through this Brook and that Bogge, till he rod him cleane off his legges, ſo that he was not able to ſtand. And thus he purchaſed indeed, the poore ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his impotent spleene, by the death of the poore Hinde, having gotten his life: But with the loſſe of that, which was as deare as Life, his owne lively hood and liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To my Thinking, this <hi>Horſe</hi> is a convenient Embleme or repreſentation of the <hi>Civill</hi> State of this Kingdome, or that part thereof, which we call the <hi>Laitie</hi> (and truly being a Lay-man my ſelfe, I was ſome what loth to uſe the familiar home lineſſe of this Compariſon, but that I have heard, that one Pope like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Common People in generall, and another Pope likened the Common People of this Nation in ſpeciall, to a Beaſt of more unworthy burthen.) And this <hi>Hinde,</hi> I have good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158516:3"/>to make an Embleme of the <hi>Spirituall</hi> State of this Kingdome, that which we call the <hi>Clergy;</hi> For I have been tol, that the Holy Ghoſt in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> comprehending all thoſe Agonies and preſſures, which from Chriſt the head, were to ſtreame and iſſue down upon his Members, the Church, hath couched them all in this one Parſon, of <hi>the Hinde of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> which our Lecturer ſayes, he thinkes, is meant by thoſe words, <hi>pro Cervomatutino,</hi> in the Latine; but he is ſure, it is the meaning of thoſe hard words, <hi>Aijeleth Shahar,</hi> in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Hebrew, which wordes are the Title of the two and twentieth Pſalme.</p>
            <p>It is yet within the memory of Man, ſince both this <hi>Horſe</hi> and this <hi>Hinde,</hi> the <hi>Laity</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> of this Land, ranne in good Paſture, up to the very belly in the Parke; that is, mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally participated and enjoyed all the bleſſed effects of Law and Government, which compaſſed and pal'd them in, on every ſide. And long might they ſo have continued, if unluckily they had not met and claſht at <hi>Watering,</hi> ſo as they did. Theſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are thoſe <hi>Waters of life;</hi> certaine poynts of <hi>Religion;</hi> and theſe Waters the <hi>Horſe</hi> had a conceit they ran not cleare, they were not fit to drinke becauſe the <hi>Hinde</hi> had Croſt them; The <hi>People</hi> ſnuffe at pretended Innovations and Superſtitions in their Religion, brought in by the <hi>Prieſt;</hi> and then whatſoever the People will imagine the Prieſt to have <hi>done,</hi> that ſhall he be ſure to ſmart for <hi>doing.</hi> Now, becauſe this <hi>Hinds</hi> was ſo quick of foot, that the <hi>Horſe</hi> had but little hopes to overtake him; becauſe the <hi>Clergy</hi> were ſo nimble with their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Antiquities, and all poynts of Learning, that the <hi>Laity</hi> could not well underſtand them; Their utmoſt reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, to compaſſe that end by <hi>Might,</hi> which could not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by <hi>Right;</hi> and to oppreſſe them with <hi>Ruine,</hi> whom they could not oppoſe with <hi>Reaſon.</hi> To this purpoſe up comes the <hi>Horſe</hi> to the very threſhold of the lodge, with his petition in his head, juſt as the <hi>Common People,</hi> came lately up to the doore of the Parliament Houſe, with Petitions in their hats, <hi>To cry for Juſtice.</hi> And the Parliament were as ready to doe them Iuſtice, as any Keeper could be; (though the Major of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158516:4"/>Iuſtice, for failing, that is, <hi>whither it were right or wrong</hi>) They would teach the <hi>Hinde</hi> to trouble the <hi>Waters,</hi> and to ſpoil more graſſe in <hi>one</hi> place, then he did eat in <hi>two:</hi> They would take an order with the <hi>Clergy</hi> for mixing <hi>Superſtition</hi> with their Religion; They would take a courſe with their <hi>Non-Reſidencies</hi> and <hi>Pluralities,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> mans enjoying of more maintenance, then would ſerve <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three;</hi> But then this <hi>Horſe</hi> muſt ſubmit unto the <hi>bridle;</hi> The <hi>Laity</hi> muſt admit of the <hi>Militia;</hi> they muſt put all the <hi>Power of the Kingdome,</hi> into the Parliaments hands; and if they doe not revenge the <hi>Horſe</hi> againſt the <hi>Hind,</hi> if they doe not lay the Pride of the <hi>Clergy</hi> low enough, then never truſt them. Never was fooliſh <hi>Horſe</hi> prouder of his golden Bit and Boſſe, then was the <hi>Common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> at firſt, of this gay bridle. It was the ſimpleſt ſight in the World, to ſee them bring in their Boles, nay their Bodkins, their Tankards, nay, their very Thimbles to <hi>Guild-hall</hi> (juſt as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did their Eare-rings) to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a <hi>Calfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed, what elſe have they now made themſelves? It is true, the poor <hi>Hinde</hi> is falne; they have had their deſires, in the ruine of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and of the Church; but, have they yet ſlipt the <hi>Bridle</hi> from their own necks? hath not the Parliament rid them to the purpoſe, now? have they not hurried them through ſuch boggs of <hi>Contributions,</hi> and ſuch bryars of <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> that have ſcratcht and tore both their <hi>Fortunes</hi> and their very <hi>Soules?</hi> have they not courſt them over <hi>hedges,</hi> that fence in their propridties and liberties? and over <hi>Gates,</hi> that opened them the free uſe and benefit of Lawes? In ſtead of ſetling the pretended <hi>Troubles</hi> in the <hi>Water</hi> of life, have they not cut a <hi>new River,</hi> and carried the water clean another way? ſo that, one knowes not where to drink when he is a dry? ſo that one knowes not where almoſt to have any Sacrament ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred as it was wont? have they not ſo long perſecuted the poore <hi>Surplice</hi> in moſt Churches, that they have ſcarce left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man a <hi>Shirt</hi> in the whole Pariſh? It is to little purpoſe to perſwade any man to that, which every man doth feele. And now the <hi>Horſe</hi> would be glad to be caſe of his Rider, if he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158516:4"/>could tell how; The <hi>People</hi> would faine returne to their old wonted Lawes and Liberties, if they could tell which way; But, alas, it is too true which the old Proverb ſaies, <hi>ſet a Begger on</hi> Horſe <hi>back and he will ride;</hi> put the power over the Lives and Liberties of the Common People, into Neceſſitous and Indigent mens hands, men that mean only to raiſe their owne Fortunes, though it be upon the whole Kingdomes ruines, And they will leave them bare and poor enough before ever they have done. Honeſt ſimple men, that were willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that, which they faine would have, were apt to receive ſome hopes of ſlipping this <hi>Bridle,</hi> at the laſt <hi>Treaty for Peace.</hi> They did imagine, that the Parliament <hi>intended</hi> a Peace, if the King were willing, as well as they <hi>pretended</hi> it; But a man with halfe an eye might ſee, they never meant it; Alas! they drive too good a <hi>trade</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to <hi>break</hi> ſuddainly; Men will talk much of ſome ground about <hi>London,</hi> how much one Acre thereof is worth; But I dare ſay, two foot of ground at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> well occupied and well manur'd, (as ſome Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men have done) hath yeelded ſome of the Farmers of all our Fortunes, greater Commoditie, and quicker Returne, then all the Land in <hi>England,</hi> which they have, beſides. And will any wiſe man think, they will ever forfeit their <hi>Leaſe</hi> for not-payment of a <hi>Pepper corne?</hi> does any man Imagine, they will looſe that Commodity, which they have got by <hi>Warre</hi> in three or foure <hi>yeares;</hi> for not offering to talke a little of <hi>Peace,</hi> for two or three <hi>dayes?</hi> Truely they did nothing elſe, ſo farre as I can ſee; and if thoſe Papers, which are printed, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all their Propoſitions, and all, the true paſſages, thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in all my life, did I never ſee the Proverbe trulier verified, <hi>A great Cry, and but a little Wooll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a noyſe is there made with <hi>Religion?</hi> (for one of their Propoſitions is concerning that) I profeſſe, I began to look about, at that; I did verily beleeve, either there was ſome Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in our <hi>Creed,</hi> or in the Doctrine of our <hi>Sacraments,</hi> or in our Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> or in our Book of nine and thirty <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> or in our Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or ſome where or other; the profeſſion whereof did much derogate from the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158516:5"/>purity of the Proteſtant Profeſſion; and I longed to ſee, what poynt of <hi>Religion</hi> that was: becauſe, having heard ſo much of the devotion and piety of the King, I could not imagine, that the Parliament and He, could differ in that; eſpecially, He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving profeſſed to maintaine the <hi>pure Proteſtant Religion,</hi> ſo often, as he hath done. Now, when all comes to all. The great buſineſſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> what doe you think it is? An <hi>aboliſhing of the Church-Government, by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> and the bringing in of a New Government whereof They themſelves are not yet agreed, what that kind of Government ſhall be; and, as appeares by their owne Books (although a man would have thought, that nothing could have ſet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Prinne</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burton</hi> together <hi>by the eares,</hi> as of late about this poynt, they both have been) it is like, they never will. And is this ſuch a great poynt of <hi>Religion,</hi> to deſtroy that Order of Men, that hath conveighe <hi>Religion</hi> unto us, ever ſince there was any, in this Iſland of ours? Is it for <hi>God's Glory,</hi> to <hi>diſhonour</hi> his <hi>Miniſters?</hi> doe the <hi>Biſhops</hi> hinder the growth of <hi>Reformation,</hi> without whom this Church of <hi>England,</hi> all the World knowes, had never been <hi>Reformed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, any man may ſee plaine, it is not the <hi>Lawne</hi> of the Biſhops, but the <hi>Land</hi> of the Biſhops, which theſe men are offended with; and they have opened their mind pretty well: for whereas, in the firſt paſſing of that Act againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> they were contented all the Biſhops Lands ſhould revert and come unto the <hi>King,</hi> (the better to bayte him, that he might catch thereat, and ſo be the more willing for to paſſe the Bill) In a later<note n="*" place="margin">See the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. IV.</note> 
               <hi>Declaration of both Kingdomes,</hi> and ſo in the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> They aſſigne thoſe very Lands unto the <hi>Scots,</hi> the payment of <hi>Publique Damages;</hi> and in concluſion, meane to reduce them, at laſt, into their owne <hi>private Purſes.</hi> If theſe men had deſired to alter the Government of the Church, and not deſired to alienate the <hi>Lands</hi> of the Church; truly, I ſhould have been ſo charitable, as to think they might have done it out of Conſcience: as beleeving the Calling of a Biſhop, unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but when I ſee, the <hi>Alteration</hi> of the one, is but made a ſhooing-horne, to draw on the <hi>Alienation</hi> of the other, (for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158516:5"/>which there is no neceſſity; for if the Office of a Biſhop be Antichriſtian, ſure, the Revenues are not; the Presbyteriall Government, or any other Government in the World, may enjoy them, as well as any private Lay-man) I cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they never meant any <hi>Publique Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> but onely the <hi>Raiſing</hi> of their own private <hi>Fortunes;</hi> that, they never lookt after any <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> which is <hi>great gaine;</hi> but after ſuch <hi>gaine,</hi> as might goe for great <hi>Godlineſſe;</hi> and if they can get that, I dare ſay for them, Religion may either <hi>ſinke</hi> or <hi>ſwim,</hi> They never care.</p>
            <p>Well, but admit, they had got all the Church Land into their handes; how doe they hope to keep it? O, let them alone for that: in the next place therefore, they offer a Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for the <hi>Militia:</hi> wherein, they deſire but two things,<note place="margin">Pag. 59. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, 73. of the Full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> firſt, the Sole <hi>Nomination of all Perſons, that ſhall be entruſted with all the Forces of this Kingdome, either by Sea or Land, without allowing the King, ſo much as the Nomination of one, whom he may</hi> Confide in; or ſo <hi>much as the Power of exception to any one,</hi> whom he hath great reaſon to diſtruſt; And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>They deſire this Power of Nomination,</hi> without <hi>any limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Time, or (as one would ſay, in plain Engliſh) <hi>For ever.</hi> And, if they ſhould not <hi>ſecure</hi> all that they have, now, they were much too blame; for who ſhall take it from them? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve me, I am ſomewhat afraid they intend ſuch a <hi>Reformation</hi> of the State, as they have done, of the <hi>Church;</hi> and then our <hi>Farmes</hi> and <hi>Copy-holds,</hi> may prove as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> as the Churches <hi>Landes,</hi> if they are worth any thing. For you know <hi>New Lords</hi> and <hi>New Lawes,</hi> ever. They may doe what they will; they have all in their owne hands; who ſhall gain-ſay them, and not be a <hi>Malignant</hi> ſtrait? But wherefore doe they deſire this, ſay they? Oh, for the <hi>ſecuring of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: and a preſervation of the Peace, when it ſhall be ſetled.</hi> I am ſure, the Kingdomes were <hi>ſecured,</hi> and the <hi>Peace</hi> was <hi>preſerved</hi> whilſt this power was wholly in the <hi>Kings</hi> hands; but ſince they have had but a fingering of it, I know not how they have <hi>ſecur'd</hi> the Kingdomes, unleſſe it be in that ſence which they uſe the word now and than; when they lay a man
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158516:6"/>faſt; and <hi>ſecure his Perſon,</hi> that is, make him ſafe, and forth-comming, when they have a mind to ruine him. So they have <hi>ſecured</hi> it, pretty well, for they have brought it into ſuch bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlavery, which our Fathers never knew; or could ever have beleeved, a Parliament would have brought it.</p>
            <p>But againſt whom would They ſecure it; againſt Forraigne Enemies? So, the King has done; and ſo, he ſtill can do. Againſt the King, becauſe they dare not truſt Him? Why, what reaſon is there in the World, if the King and the Parliament be jealous and fearfull one of anothers power, but the King ſhould be ſecured againſt his Feares of the Parliament, as well as the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament be ſecur'd againſt their Feares of the King? To that end, was the King, it ſhould appeare, content to divide and ſhare His Power with the Parliament, (a thing, which was never yet knowne ſince the Conqueſt, untill now) and to give them leave to chooſe halfe thoſe perſons that ſhould have the power of this <hi>Militia,</hi> and to name the other halfe himſelfe. But this would not be accepted; They muſt name all, or none; becauſe,<note place="margin">Pag. 92. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 136. of the Full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> they ſay, if <hi>the Perſons ſhould be ſeverally named,</hi> ſome by the King, and ſome by them: <hi>It is probable,</hi> they <hi>would act, according to their ſeverall Intereſts; and the Warre thereby would be the more eaſily revived.</hi> Why, but if it be onely <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,</hi> They would doe ſo; then it is <hi>probable</hi> too, that they would not doe ſo: for <hi>probabilities</hi> are incident to <hi>both</hi> ſides; and if it be <hi>but</hi> probable, that men named by both Parties, ſhould act according to their ſeverall Intereſts: it may be <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,</hi> that men named by both parties, may have no ſuch ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Intereſts; but may conſcientiouſly and honeſtly intend one and the ſame End, the publique Peace of the Kingdome, and the preſervation of the juſt Prerogatives of the King. How ſoever, if it be ſo <hi>probable,</hi> that men named on both ſides, will act according to their ſeverall Intereſts, and ſome doe what they can for the King who named them, and the others doe what they can for the Parliament, who named them; Certainly, it is more <hi>probable,</hi> that men onely named by the Parliament, will act according to that Intereſt of theirs, and ſo doe all for the Parliament, and nothing for the King; whereby,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158516:6"/>the Warre indeed, is not like to be revived; but the whole State of Monarchy to be ruined; the Prince being brought in ſubjection to His People; and having neither power to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his Enemies, or to ſuccour his Friends. And truly for my part, if I muſt live in ſubjection, as the State, to which God hath call'd me; I had rather live in ſubjection to One, then to Foure hundred; to One, whom God hath made my Superiour, then to foure hundred, whom I my ſelfe, and ſome others no wiſer then I, have made; and muſt unmake them too, I think, before we ſhall be quiet; for if they Rule and Command, a little longer, ſo, as they have done: I am afraid, they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get quite to Obey; ſpecially, being never very well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Rules thereof, or having ever been deſirous much, to learne them.</p>
            <p>Their third Propoſition is concerning <hi>Ireland;</hi> wherein they demand three things more. 1. The declaring of the late <hi>Ceſſation</hi> made, to be quite voyd, and utterly unlawfull. 2. The proſecution of the Warre in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be put into their handes, to be managed by a Committee of both Kingdomes, ſome whereof are to be <hi>Engliſh</hi> and ſome <hi>Scotch.</hi> And 3. The Nomination of the Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Iuſtices of both Benches. Truly, all good men I think, doe deteſt and abhorre that bloudy Rebellion in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and although they ſtreine reaſonable well, to ſet it out in its owne Colours, when they call them <hi>bloudy Rebels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 121. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 174. of the Full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>Antichriſtian Rebels,</hi> (though I could have wiſht they had made no mention of their <hi>Covenant,</hi> for feare the World hereafter be miſtaken, it looks ſo like their owne) <hi>Men that have broke all the Lawes of God and Man, their Faith, their Allegiance, all bonds of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c.</hi> Yet, if they ſhould have uſed more ſevere expreſſions of them, and Imprecations upon them, I think no good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but would have ſaid, Amen. But then, <hi>woe be to the Geeſe, when the Foxe preaches,</hi> as they uſe to ſay; God help all good and honeſt Subjects, when the greateſt Rebels in the World, profeſſe againſt Rebellion, and cry out upon it. For, as for thoſe Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they did nothing but what <hi>their</hi> Religion will avow: They make no Conſcience of <hi>keeping Faith with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158516:7"/>Heretiques,</hi> and therefore, by their owne rules, it is a leſſe ſinne for them, to <hi>breake their Oathes,</hi> and their <hi>Allegiance;</hi> But for our Rebels of <hi>England,</hi> every thing which they doe, their own <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> doth diſclaime: Did ever the Proteſtant Religion allow Subjects to take Armes againſt their owne Native King? and yet theſe men will take them. Did ever the Proteſtant Religion ſuffer men to violate their Faiths, and break their Oathes, which they have ſwore both to God, and Men? and yet theſe men will break them; nay, and think they doe God good ſervice, in the violation thereof.</p>
            <p>For God's ſake, how comes it to paſſe, that the King did ſo pleaſe the Engliſh; in making the late <hi>Pacification</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and does now ſo diſpleaſe them, in making the late <hi>Ceſſation</hi> in <hi>Ireland?</hi> Is it becauſe the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were <hi>Rebels;</hi> ſurely, ſo were They. Is it becauſe the <hi>Scots</hi> only fought for their <hi>Liberties</hi> and their <hi>Religion?</hi> ſurely, ſo did They. But, you will ſay; their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is a <hi>falſe</hi> Religion; So will they ſay of <hi>yours:</hi> and ſo long as it is true in their Opinion, and to their Conſcience, it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as lawfull for them, to fight for that Religion, which they believe to be True, though it be false; as it is for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells to fight for that Religion, which is, both believed to be, and is alſo, True. But the plain truth is, whither or no, there was that neceſſity for the <hi>Pacification,</hi> I will not meddle; but ſure enough of this <hi>Ceſſation,</hi> there was the greateſt neceſſity that ever could be; for the Lords and Iuſtices of <hi>Ireland,</hi> wrote moſt lamentable Letters to the King,<note place="margin">See the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lords Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, pag. 194. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 10. in the Appendix.</note> complaining that they wanted bread; That they had not proviſion for one Month; and not a Hundred barrells of Powder in all their ſtore, which would not laſt them above a Moneth; and that the Parliament knowing of all theſe neceſſities, never ſent them in whole ſix Moneths, but fourteen tunne of Cheeſe, and three ſcore and fifteen barrells of butter, which would not ſerve that part of the Army which lay about <hi>Dublin,</hi> for above ſeaven or eight daies; and they humbly beſeech the King, to think of ſome expedient courſe, as ſoon as may be, to preſerve His whole Kingdom from imminent and apparent ruine. Now what could the King doe for them in ſuch a caſe? Send victualls, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158516:7"/>Monies, or Ammunition, He could not, for He neither had them; nor the uſe of His own Shipps to conveigh them, if He had. Send to the Parliament He might; and to as much pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as before thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> did; for they that could have the conſcience to ſpend a Hundred thouſand pounds of the mony which was collected for <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was none of their owne,<note place="margin">Pag. 135. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 177. of the Full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> upon the maintaining of this their Rebellion here in <hi>England</hi> (as they dare not deny themſelves to have done) it is ſomewhat unlikely, they would part with any thing that was their own, when nothing but charity, could compell them thereunto.</p>
            <p>Well, but they ſay, that by <hi>undeniable proofs it is moſt cleare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 133. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 177. in their Paper of the 22. of <hi>Feb.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that theſe neceſſities alleadged for the grounds of the Ceſſation, were made by the deſigne of the Popiſh and Prelaticall party in England and Ireland.</hi> But, me thinks, if the <hi>proofes</hi> be ſo <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable,</hi> they ſhould be <hi>demonſtrable.</hi> I could never meet with any thing that did look like a proof thereof in all thoſe papers. I confeſſe this had been ſomewhat, if it had been true. But the Rebels doe not offer ſo good proofe of that, which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, as that proof is, which is offered for the contrary, which notwithſtanding, they will not accept; for, to prove the want of neceſſary proviſion for reliefe of that miſerable Kingdom, there are diverſe Letters produced by the Kings Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, from the Lords Iuſtices, and the Councell of <hi>Ireland;</hi> the Truth whereof, they ſeem not willing to believe, unleſſe they may ſee the names of thoſe men who did ſubſcribe them (and yet they will not promiſe indempnity to their perſons if they ſhould ſee them; or, that it ſhould be no prejudice unto them, if they ſhould fall into their hands; for upon thoſe tearmes, they might have ſeen them, when they would) But, to prove that theſe neceſſities were contrived by the Popiſh and Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall party both in England and in Ireland, they produce not ſo much as any Letter, either under <hi>many</hi> mens hands, or, <hi>one;</hi> not bring the leaſt evidence thereof, other then their own Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, unworthy ſurmiſes; and the <hi>conſideration of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances;</hi> Now I would have the World Iudge, whether there be not more apparent proofe, from Letters under mens hands,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158516:8"/>that live upon the place, and were lamentable witneſſes, and ſufferers in the neceſſities of that Kingdome, that there was no reliefe at all ſent them, from the Parliament; Then there is from their ſimple affirmations, that thoſe releifes were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of by the Popiſh and Prelaticall party, for the ſuccour and aſſiſtance of the Rebells, in their greateſt wants. And yet theſe Rebels of <hi>England</hi> will have us beleive any thing which they affirme upon their own words, although they are Parties in the Cauſe, and will not beleive us upon the Letters and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of the Lords and Councell of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly were the beſt Iudges therein. Beſides, in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if the Popiſh and Prelaticall party had had ſuch a hand in doing the Rebels ſervice, certainly they would have found ſome better comfort then they did, in receiving of their Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; The Rebels could not chuſe but be favourable to their Perſons and their Eſtates, and give them liberty to enjoy them, in ſome meaſure. But it is too apparent, that, although the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties of this Rebellion, have fallen upon all the Kings good Subjects there in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet they have fallen thicker upon no condition of men, then upon the <hi>Prelats;</hi> ſome whereof have received ſixteen or ſeaventeen wounds from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and bin left for dead; others have bin rob'd and plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their very ſhirts; and all, or the moſt Part of them, have bin driven out of That Kingdom into This, for the very ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their Lives, where they remaine in great diſtreſſe and neceſſities, not having ſcarſly how to get them Bread.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe men muſt have <hi>this Ceſſation made voyd,</hi> and the farther <hi>proſecution of the Warre,</hi> committed to their hands. Truly I dare ſay, if there were a Peace, here, the King would ſo farre accept of their Aſſiſtance, in the rooting out of that Rebellion, as is fit, either for him to take, or them to give: I dare ſay, they could propoſe no likely way of reducing thoſe Rebels, but the King would be willing ſtrait to practice it. But, whilſt they are in actuall Rebellion here againſt him; whilſt they manage <hi>one</hi> Warre here againſt him: For him to entruſt them with the managing of <hi>another</hi> Warre, there, for him; Were ſuch a piece of weakneſſe, as no man certainly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158516:8"/>can be perſwaded to, but he, that will be perſwaded to give a man two to one, that is ſcarce able to play with him on even hands.</p>
            <p>And, as concerning their Nomination of the Lievtenant in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Iudges of both Benches, it ſeemes to me the greateſt piece of Arrogance that was ever yet heard off. Have they not enough, that they are Kings themſelves; but they muſt make Kings, too? but, I could be contented, if men were <hi>arrogant</hi> onely, if they were not <hi>abſurd</hi> alſo; For I demand; The Nomination of the Lievtenant, either it was in the Kings Power, before they deſired it to be granted them, or it was not; If it was not in his power, then, they are <hi>abſur'd</hi> to aske that, which they know, was not in the Kings Power to Give: If it were; then they are <hi>abſur'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 136. n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 178. of the Full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>not to admit the Marqueſſe of Ormond,</hi> for a Lievtenant, whom all the World knowes the King had Nominated; before ever They deſired this power of Nomination; as in expreſſe termes, they ſay, they <hi>doe not,</hi> in their Paper of the <hi>22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if ſuch a ſimple man, as I, can ſee theſe Demands of the Parliament to be unreaſonable, ſenceleſſe, and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: Surely, thoſe men that were Commiſſioners for the King, and had more wit and underſtanding, then I, could ſee further into them; No doubt, but they ſaw, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and granting of them muſt needs inferre, a totall <hi>Alteration and Change,</hi> both in our <hi>Spirituall,</hi> and in our <hi>Civill</hi> Government; both in our Church, and in our State; and God deliver me, and every honeſt man, from living to behold that day. Wee have by wofull Experience found, what the want of Epiſcopall Government hath wrought in the Church, already: for no man knowes almoſt, of what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion his Neighbour is today, or, of what he himſelfe ſhall be, to morrow; by our ſad ſufferings, we have learnt, what it is, to ſee dayes, when there is <hi>no King in Iſrael;</hi> or as good as none; when His Subjects ſeek to diveſt and ſpoile Him of His Rights and Power. Before, we could complaine, if we thought the King broke any Law; but now, we doe not know our ſelves, what is Law, till we have broke it.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158516:9"/>It is not as it was once in Saint <hi>Paul; I had not knowne ſinne, but by the Law;</hi> but it is now, I had <hi>not knowne Law, but by the ſinne;</hi> for every thing that a good man does in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to God, or Obedience to his King, is therefore made a crime, becauſe he does it, though it never had any ſuch name, before.</p>
            <p>I, but you will ſay, if the Cauſe of the Parliament be ſuch a bad Cauſe, that they are abſolute and direct <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt the King; how come ſo many men to be of that ſide? True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I confeſſe, the Cauſe is a good Cauſe <hi>to live in</hi> (for if a man take that ſide, he is likely to ſave his owne ſtake, and he is like enough to get a good ſhare in many other mens;) But give me a Cauſe to <hi>live in,</hi> and <hi>to dye in</hi> too; A Cauſe, which, if it yeeld me no profit whilſt <hi>I live,</hi> ſhall notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding yeeld me pleaſure when <hi>I dye;</hi> and the comfort of this Conſideration, that I have not ſtayned my Conſcience, for any baſe and beggarly reſpects of this World, but have kept it cleane, both towards the Lord, and towards his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted; as no doubt, but every man is bound to doe. And certainly there is more in it, then, every ſimple Country-fellow like my ſelfe, imagines; That, on the Parliament ſide, ſo many men of note and quality, when They have their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about them before they dye, doe familiarly renounce this wicked and ungodly courſe, and profeſſe, they undertooke it for meere gaine, or ſome baſer end, (as from Colonell <hi>Sandys,</hi> who dyed at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> in the beginning of this Warre, to Major <hi>Abercromie</hi> who dyed by us, but a little while agoe, many poore Soules afflicted which the ſence of their Rebellion have done) When, on the Kings ſide, there was never yet heard one man of any condition whatſoever, (though reduced to the greateſt exigence, and want that man could be) that ever repented him of taking up Armes, and ſpending his life in His Majeſties Cauſe and Service.</p>
            <p>I know it weighes much with many of my Neighbours, That the Rebels uſe Country people kindly, where they come, and uſe to <hi>pay for what they have,</hi> when the Kings Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers doe not; And ſo, they are ready to Judge of the <hi>goodneſſe</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:158516:9"/>of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> by the purſes of their <hi>Cuſtomers;</hi> and truly, this wrought a pretty good opinion of them, once even in me my ſelfe; but when I had conſidered a little better, how theſe men come by that Money, (even by robbing and plundering the King and His good Subjects, for otherwiſe they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have a penny) I beganne to think that as they were direct <hi>Theeves,</hi> ſo we that took their Monies, were but little better then <hi>Receivers;</hi> and the curſe of thoſe poor People, who are deſpoyled of their Eſtates, to furniſh them with monies, muſt doubtleſſe light upon us.</p>
            <p>Beſides; alas, what is the poore <hi>Horſe</hi> the better (when he hath been ridden into a ſweat, from head to foot, and is ſearce able to ſtand) for a little ſtroking and clapping on the ſhoulder? What are the poore people of the Country, the better, for receiving ſome few pence, <hi>from</hi> them, when they muſt pay it out againe, by whole pounds <hi>unto</hi> Them? They doe but <hi>ſteale a Gooſe, and ſtick up a Feather,</hi> as we uſe to ſay; For at laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween faire meanes and foule, they leave us nothing. But all this while, what is become of the <hi>Liberty of the Subject,</hi> which made ſuch a noyſe, at the beginning of theſe Warres? In all the Twenty dayes Treaty, not a word of that, on their Side; And when the Kings Commiſſioners deſired to have the Kings Propoſitions Treated on, which inſiſted much upon this poynt, They could never have an Anſwer. All this while, what is become of the <hi>Lawes of the Land,</hi> which every man thought at firſt, theſe men did onely fight for? In all the Twenty dayes Treaty, not one word, of the breach of any <hi>one</hi> Law of the Land, with which they taxe the King; but they rather invite Him to breake <hi>many,</hi> if He would be perſwaded unto it; For there was ſcarce any one thing, in all the Treaty which they deſired of the King, which was not directly againſt the known <hi>Lawes of the Land,</hi> which they have all this time, pretended to defend. Nay, when the King (to ſhew how zealous He was of the preſervation of the <hi>Lawes</hi>) deſired in His Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, That <hi>nothing might be avowed,</hi> but that <hi>every Act might be diſclaimed on both Sides,</hi> which was <hi>not according to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158516:10"/>the knowne Law;</hi> They would never Treat of that Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or give any Anſwer to it. All this while, what is become of <hi>Fetching the King up unto His Parliament,</hi> which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out, as the ſole reaſon for the raiſing of ſo many ſeverall Armies, as have been raiſed? In all the Twenty dayes Treaty, not a ſyllable of <hi>that,</hi> on their part; Nay, when the Kings Commiſſioners, had propoſed it unto them, and deſired to Treat with them, concerning <hi>His Majeſties speedy Returne to Weſtminſter,</hi> whereby an End might be put to theſe unhappy Diſtractions and Diviſions; They utterly refus'd to Treat with them, therein; and choſe rather, to break up the <hi>Treaty,</hi> (when they might have prolonged it, if they had pleaſed, for ſo they were earneſtly deſired to doe, by our Commiſſioners) then to allow <hi>That,</hi> for the Subject matter of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore, reſting well aſſured, by theſe proceedings of theirs, in the late Treaty, that they of Weſtminſter aime at nothing but their own Greatneſſe; and intend to rule perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, both over the King and Kingdome; purpoſing to change that auncient Government of <hi>Kings</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> as they have chang'd that other of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> I deſire all my Countrymen, to lay it to their hearts; whether they had not better venture their lives <hi>once,</hi> then be ſure to looſe both their Livelyhoods and Liberties <hi>for ever:</hi> Whither they had not better help to make an end of the <hi>Warre;</hi> then live, and linger out their lives and Fortunes, in the vaine expectation of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended <hi>Peace.</hi> Whither they had not rather their <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> ſhould raigne, then that their <hi>Servants ſhould rule over them,</hi> which is one of the pittifull complaints of <hi>Zion,</hi> in her prayer to God, in the fift of the <hi>Lamentations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this they may truſt to, that, by the bleſſing of God, (who never expoſes the perſon or the Cauſe of Kings to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or miſcarriage, but for the Peoples ſinne) They may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in a very ſhort time, both their <hi>Liberties, Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-hoods</hi> and yet ſave their <hi>Lives;</hi> And, if the Countries here abouts, would but riſe and take up Armes (as they ſhould doe, not only for the Kings ſake, but for their own, if they did well
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158516:10"/>conſider it) leſſe then <hi>Three Months,</hi> with Gods help, would put an end to the Miſeries of more then <hi>Three yeares,</hi> that are <hi>paſt;</hi> and prevent the Miſeries of many yeares, which are yet to <hi>come,</hi> if ſome ſuch courſe, as this, be not timely taken; for out of doubt, ſo long as God ſhall ſend either the King or any of His Children, Life; there will never be wanting thoſe true-hearted Engliſhmen, that will ſpend their bloud, in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their juſt Intereſts and Rights: Which I doe as firmely believe they will recover, either <hi>firſt</hi> or <hi>laſt,</hi> as I doe any one thing in this World, which is not Scripture.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
